<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise tending to unitie in a sermon preached at Droghedah on Whitsunday (being the ninth of Iune 1622.) before the Kings Majesties Commissioners for Ireland. By Henry Leslie.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102368</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838153</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838153</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2516</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05349)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2516)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 805:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise tending to unitie in a sermon preached at Droghedah on Whitsunday (being the ninth of Iune 1622.) before the Kings Majesties Commissioners for Ireland. By Henry Leslie.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Societie of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2516:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2516:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE TENDING TO VNITIE: <hi>IN</hi> A SERMON PREACHED AT DROGHEDAH ON WHITSVNDAY (being the ninth of Iune 1622.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kings Majeſties Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners for IRELAND.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Leſlie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Quoties dicimus, toties judicamur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hierom.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>DUBLIN, Printed by the Societie of Stationers. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2516:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2516:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHER IN GOD, CHRISTOPHER, by Gods providence <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Ardmagh, <hi>Primate of all Ireland,</hi> and Metropolitan, and one of his Maieſties moſt honourable Privie Councell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MOST REVEREND;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was by your Graces direction that this Sermon was preached; and now by the ſame appointment it is publiſhed: that the world may ſee it contayneth nothing but truth, and is free from undiſcreet raylings, wherewith it was charged by them who dare adventure to cenſure us before they heare us.</p>
            <p>Now theſe my ſmall labours, and the labours of ſome few dayes, being the first fruits of my weake engine, I here preſent unto your Grace, to whom I owe my ſelfe, and all I have, much more my ſervice, with the labour of my hands, head and heart, as most boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Indeed this ſmall offering is no more equivalent to my debt, than a mole-hill is to a mountaine: But whatſoever my barren ground can afford, ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:2516:3"/>at your Honours command: to which moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly I proſtrate my ſelfe, praying alwayes, that God would be pleaſed to continue your Grace long unto this poore Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that like another <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> you may build up the walls of this decayed <hi>IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RUSALEM.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt bounden Chaplaine, HENRY LESLY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2516:3"/>
            <head>A TREATISE TENDING TO <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>I. TIM. II. V.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For there is one God, and one Mediator between God and men, the man Christ Ieſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nder the Old Teſtament they obſerved the Feaſt of Pentecoſt in remembrance of the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at Sinai: ſo it hath beene the practiſe of the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the New Teſtament, to keep the like Feaſt, at the ſame time, in remembrance of the Goſpell which came from Ieruſalem. For if the Law ſhould be thus honoured, which is the miniſtration of death,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.7.</note> how much more the Goſpell, which is the miniſtration of life, and that not written in tables of ſtone, as was the Law, but in the tables of our hearts by the holy Spirit? for this Spirit did deſcend upon the Apoſtles in a viſible ſhape on the day of Pentecoſt,<note place="margin">Act. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> according to Chriſts promiſe, that hee would ſend unto them another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.16, 17, 26.</note> even the Spirit of truth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.13. 1. Cor. 2.10.</note> to leade them into all truth, to teach them all things, even the deepe things of God. So that thoſe great and ſecret myſteries, which under the Old Teſtament were ſhut up from the people,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2516:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>like unto the Sanctuarie, into which entrance was ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome made; are now made open to the underſtanding of all the faithfull: for this Spirit hath revealed them unto the Apoſtles, and the Apoſtles in their writings have cleerely taught them unto us. Even in theſe few words which I have read, behold a bundle of theſe myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but obſcurely known in former times, now plainly ſet forth unto us: as the myſterie of the Godhead, of our reconciliation to God, of Chriſts mediation, and of his incarnation. <hi>There is one God, and one mediator betweene God and men, the man Christ Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words containe the ſumme of the Goſpell, and chiefe heads of our Chriſtian faith, catechiſing us plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſixe maine grounds and principles of Religion: I. That there is a God, elſe how ſhould he be <hi>one?</hi> II. that this God is <hi>one; there is one God.</hi> III. that this one God is reconciled and made one with us by a mediator; for <hi>there is a mediator betweene God and men.</hi> IV. that this mediator is one; <hi>and one mediator.</hi> V. that Chriſt Ieſus is this one mediator. VI. that Chriſt Ieſus is a man; <hi>the man Christ Ieſus. There is one God, and one mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and men, the man Christ Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus hee leadeth us by the hand from thoſe things which are moſt commonly knowne and received, to theſe that be leſſe manifeſt, everie one of theſe principles revealing unto us a greater myſterie, and further degree of knowledge. For the firſt, that there is a God is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all men. The ſecond, that this God is one, is not ſo commonly knowne as the former; for the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles worſhipped a multitude of gods: yet is it generally confeſſed, not only by the Church, but alſo by the wiſeſt of the Heathen. The third, that this God is reconciled to us by a mediator, exceeds the knowledge of all Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles whatſoever, who had nothing but the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2516:4"/>for it is not knowne by nature, but by revelation from God; yet is it granted by manie falſe teachers, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Iewes, and alſo others who receive but a parcell of Gods word. But the fourth, that this mediator is one, is leſſe manifeſt yet: for it is refuſed by the Papiſts, yet received by the Iewes. But the fift, that Chriſt Ieſus is this one mediator, doth exceed their faith alſo: yet is it acknowledged by manie Heretickes, who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding denied the humane nature of Chriſt. So that the ſixt and laſt, that Chriſt Ieſus is a man, is moſt hid and privie, as being the proper faith of the true Church.</p>
            <p>As every one of theſe principles revealeth a further degree of knowledge; ſo alſo a greater meaſure of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. The firſt, that there is a God, to whom wee may have recourſe in the day of trouble, is a great comfort to us: but if there were manie Gods, ſo that wee knew not to which of them we ſhould runne for help, our comfort were but ſmall; therefore the ſecond principle ſhewes that this God is onely one. But albeit there be a God, and onely one God; yet if we be at enmitie with him, wee have greater cauſe to feare than to reioyce: in the third place therefore, hee removeth this feare, ſhewing that there is a mediator by whom man is reconciled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. But yet if there were not one, but manie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators, and wee knew not to whom rather to betake us, what better ſhould we be? therefore in the fourth hee taketh away this doubt alſo, affirming that there is one mediator. But though there be but one mediator, yet what if he be unknowne to us? wee are ſtill as before: therefore the fift poſition leades us, by the hand, unto the particular perſon, Chriſt Ieſus, who is this one me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator. But what of all this, if Chriſt Ieſus be only God, and ſo as ſtrange to us as the pattic it ſelfe with whom we are at enmitie? therefore to make our ioy full, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2516:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſixt principle tells us that hee is a man. A man, and ſo neare unto us, not in place, for hee is contayned within the heavens according to his manhood: but neare unto us in blood; for he is a brother of ours, bone of our bone, and fleſh of our fleſh: and neare unto us in affection; for he hath compaſsionate bowels, he is touched with a feeling of our infirmities,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> and was in all ſorts tempted in like ſort as we are, yet without ſinne. And ſo foraſmuch as Chriſt Ieſus is a man, wee may goe boldly unto him, and by him have acceſſe unto the one God, he being the only mediator betweene God and man. This is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all comfort. So this Text is like <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, ariſing ſtep by ſtep till it bring us to comfort. My ſpeech then at this time, ſhall as it were climbe up by theſe ſixe ſtaires;
<list>
                  <item>1. That there is a God:</item>
                  <item>2. That this God is one:</item>
                  <item>3. That he is made one with us by a mediator:</item>
                  <item>4. That the mediator is one:</item>
                  <item>5. That this one mediator is Chriſt:</item>
                  <item>6. That Chriſt Ieſus is a man.</item>
               </list>
In handling whereof, you will perceive me to omit manie points that are incident; for I muſt attend upon the time, and aime at the occaſion.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, that there is a God; I ſhould ſpend my breath in vaine, if I ſhould labour to prove it: for it is ingrafted into every mans heart by nature, and plainely taught by all the dumbe and ſenſeleſſe creatures; ſo that never man denied it but a foole, <hi>The foole ſaith in his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.1. Rom. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>there is no God, Pſal. 14.1.</hi> Therefore as it is preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in my Text, ſo ſhall it be in my ſpeech.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, that this God is one; whereby three things are ſignified of God: that he is indiviſible, one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not manie: that he is immutable and unchangeable, one and the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever: and that he is without all reſpect of perſons, one and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to all ſorts of men. Firſt, God is one, that is, indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2516:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>one only, and not manie; according to that, 1. Cor. 8.6. <hi>Vnto us there is but one God.</hi> So doth the Nicen Creed acknowledge, <hi>I beleeve in one God:</hi> For God (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) is <hi>Vniſsimus,</hi> moſt one. <hi>Si non est unus, non est,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian;</hi> either one or none. Here wee muſt take heed of ſundry wicked errors and hereſies on each ſide: on the right hand, we have thoſe who acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed manie Gods: on the left hand, wee have thoſe who doe ſo farre maintaine God to be one, that they fall upon the other extremitie, to denie that there are three perſons ſubſiſting in this one God, or divine nature. And of either ſide there be ſeverall ſorts, differing one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as they do all from the truth: all which I forbeare to remember, as unworthie to be named at all, unfit to be mentioned in the Pulpit. It is enough for you to know, that amids thoſe rocks on everie ſide, our ſafeſt courſe is to hold the middle way, ſo acknowledging God to be one, that we denie him not alſo to be three: one in eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, but three in perſon, the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt; diſtinct each from other by their perſonall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties, the Father being from none, the Sonne from the Father, the Holy Ghoſt from them both: yet not divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one from another, becauſe there is but one divine eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, which being infinite, is all and whole in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all &amp; whole in the Sonne, all and whole in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: Therefore (ſaith <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creed) <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Pater, Deus Filius, Deus Spiritus Sanctus, &amp; tamen non tres Dij, ſed unus Deus.</hi> For (ſaith he) <hi>as we are compelled by the Christian verity, to acknowledge every perſon by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be God; ſo are we forbidden by the Catholicke Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to ſay there be three Gods. So that in all things, unitie in trinitie, and trinitie in unitie is to be worſhipped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot ſtand here to confirme the truth of this by teſtimonie out of Scripture: only to ſay ſomething in a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2516:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>word; for the unitie of Gods nature, take my Text for a ſufficient proofe, <hi>There is one God.</hi> and for the trinitie and diſtinction of the perſons, I will onely alledge one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which I am occaſioned by this preſent feaſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; When the Holy Ghoſt did deſcend upon the Apoſtles on this day: there ye have a diſtinction of all the three perſons. The third perſon he is ſent, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in a viſible ſhape of cloven tongues: the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he ſends him: and the ſecond, by interceding with the firſt perſon, procureth the third perſon to be ſent. So doth our Saviour diſtinguiſh them, Ioh. 14.16. <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another comforter.</hi> there is the Sonne, praying to the Father, that the Comforter, which is the holy Spirit, might be given unto the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples: and therefore thoſe three muſt be diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, foraſmuch as ſeverall actions are aſcribed to everie one of them in the ſame worke that was done on this day.</p>
            <p>The Fathers, to expreſſe this incomprehenſible my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, have uſed ſundry ſimilitudes taken from things naturall; as the ſimilitude of the ſoule of man, wherein there be three diſtinct faculties, and yet but one eſſence of them all. The ſimilitude of the fountaine; the ſtreame flowing from it, and the river flowing from them both: which being three diſtinct things, yet for ſubſtance are but one water. The ſimilitude of a tree, wherein there be three diſtinct things, the roote, the ſtocke, and the branch: the root depending from none, the ſtocke from the root, and the branch from them both; yet all are but one tree. Finally, the light of the Sunne, the light of the Moone, and the light of the ayre, are three diſtinct lights: the light of the Sunne is from none, the light of the Moone is from the Sunne, and the light of the ayre from them both, and yet for ſubſtance they are but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2516:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>one and the ſame light. Even ſo the Father, the Sonne, the Holy Ghoſt, are three diſtinct perſons: the Father from none, the Sonne from the Father, the Holy Ghoſt from them both, &amp; yet all three are but one God. But for all theſe ſimilitudes, we muſt acknowledge with <hi>Cyprian, Nulla creatura talis eſſe potest, qualis est creator; ideo ſicut ſine exemplo eſt divina eſſentia; ita ſine exemplo est divina majestas:</hi> as there is no creature ſuch as is the creator, ſo there is no example can expreſſe either the eſſence, or the maieſtie of GOD. For this is a myſterie of myſteries, farre ſurpaſsing the reach of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of anie creature: which the Seraphims profeſſe, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 6.2. when at the preſence of this one God, they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their faces with their wings, acknowledging their inabilitie to behold, much leſſe to comprehend, ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by this that God is one, is ſignified that hee is immutable and unchangeable,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> one and the ſame (as ſaith the Apoſtle) yeſterday and to day, and the ſame for ever. In this ſenſe it may be, God is called one, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.20. <hi>But God is one.</hi> He is one or immutable in his nature, in his decrees, in his actions. His nature or eſſence is one and the ſame immutable and unchangeable, becauſe he is voyde of all kinde of compoſition, both phyſicall and metaphyſicall, and (as wee ſpeake in the Schooles) <hi>actus purus.</hi> So that he is not ſubiect unto anie change, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſider his being, or his attributes: for if wee reſpect his being, he is eternall, that is, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, without end, and alwayes the ſame: for as time, being (as the Philoſopher defines it) <hi>men ſura motus per prius &amp; posterius:</hi> hath in it three things; there is <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium, ſucceſsio &amp; finis:</hi> even ſo eternitie, which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to time, muſt be free of all theſe, free from beginning, from end, and from all change or ſucceſsion So <hi>Phavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2516:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath obſerved, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth one, <hi>qui non ſolum non deſinit eſſe, ſed neque etiam deſinit talis eſſe.</hi> and this word is uſed of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. So that, as I ſaid, he is not only without beginning and without end, but alſo while hee is, hee is ever the ſame; as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.25. <hi>Thou hast laid the foundations of the earth, and the heavens are the workes of thy hand. They ſhall periſh, but thou ſhalt endure, yea all of them ſhall waxe olde like a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: as a vesture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed. But thou art the ſame, and thy yeares ſhall have no end.</hi> And as his Being, ſo alſo his Attributes are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, not ſubiect to anie change: his Iuſtice, his Mercie, his Wiſedome, his Power, all are immutable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, for they are his verie nature: whatſoever is in God, is God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Againe, he is one and the ſame in his Will his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and his Decrees: for <hi>God is not as man that he ſhould lye, neither as the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent. hath he ſaid, and ſhall he not doe it? hath he ſpoken, and ſhall hee not accompliſh it?</hi> Numb 23.19. <hi>I am the Lord and change not,</hi> Mal. 3.6. <hi>My counſaile ſhall ſtand, and my will ſhall be done,</hi> Iſai. 46.10. For when one changeth his purpoſe, it is either becauſe hee ſeeth that his purpoſe is not good, at leaſt, that hee might have purpoſed better than hee did: or elſe it is becauſe he perceiveth that he cannot bring to paſſe his former purpoſe; and ſo the change of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile doth argue either want of wiſedome, or want of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. But God wanteth neither of them; he is, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes was, the ſame moſt wiſe God, and ſo could not have taken anie better counſaile, than that which hee tooke from all eternitie. And as hee is moſt wiſe, ſo alſo omnipotent, able to effect all his counſailes: <hi>Hee doth whatſoever he will,</hi> Pſal. 115.3. <hi>Yea who hath reſisted his will?</hi> Rom. 9.19. And therefore that doctrine of the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilitie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2516:7"/>of Gods predeſtination, as it is contrary to the Scripture, which teacheth that <hi>Gods purpoſe according to election, must ſtand,</hi> Rom. 9.11. ſo it is moſt blaſphemous againſt God. For, to ſay that Gods predeſtination may be changed, that the elect may become reprobate, and ſo damned, and on the contrarie, the reprobate become e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and ſo ſaved; is as much as to ſay that Gods abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Will, which is himſelfe, may be changed, that his Preſcience or Knowledge may be deceived, that his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent power may be weakened, that his actions may be impeded, and ſo that God may become no God.</p>
            <p>Finally, he is one and the ſame in his actions; which may be declared three maner of wayes: 1. where the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is the ſame, Gods action is of the ſame kinde: for example; Did God in former times execute his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt rebellious ſinners? ye may be ſure that he will doe the like now. Upon this ground the Apoſtle reaſoneth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.21. <hi>For if God ſpared not the naturall branches, take heed least he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, They were caſt off becauſe of unbeleefe, and if thou fall into the ſame ſinne, thou may be ſure to taſte of the ſame puniſhment; foraſmuch as where the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is the ſame, Gods actions are alwayes the ſame. So the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. alledgeth Gods iudgements upon the Iewes in the wilderneſſe: and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> the great iudgements upon the Angels that ſinned, upon the old world, and upon Sodome and Gomorrhe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. concluding from thence, That if he ſpared not them, ſo neither will he ſpare us, if wee doe as they did. <hi>For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven, againſt all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and unrighteouſneſſe of men, Rom.</hi> 1.18. Againe, hath God in former times performed mercie and deliverance to his owne people? yee may be ſure that he will doe the ſame ſtill. Upon this ground <hi>David</hi> built his aſſurance;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2516:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>The Lord that delivered me out of the paw of the Lion, and out of the paw of the Beare, he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philistim,</hi> 1. Sam. 17.37. And ſo in manie places of the Pſalmes, where hee lamenteth the miſeries of the Church, he reckoneth up Gods former benefites beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon her, that by the experience of Gods former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, both himſelfe and others might be aſſured of a future deliverance; foraſmuch as God is alwayes the ſame, viſiting the iniquities of the fathers upon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the third and fourth generation of them that hate him, and ſhewing mercie unto thouſands of them that love him, and keepe his commandements. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God is one and the ſame in his actions, as being the ſame meanes to bring men to the ſame end. There is not one way for the Iewes to be ſaved, another for the Gentiles, but <hi>it is one God which ſhall justifie circumciſion by faith, and uncircumciſion through faith;</hi> Rom. 3.30. There is for all, the ſame Saviour, Chriſt; the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, Faith; the ſame degrees of ſalvation intervee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning betweene Gods decree and the execution thereof, namely, Vocation, Iuſtification, Santification; and the ſame outward meanes, Gods Word and Sacraments. But here wee muſt remember, that albeit God worketh the ſame things in all the faithfull, yet not in the ſame meaſure and degree. He did illuminate his Saints under the old Teſtament, but not in that meaſure that he doth his people under the Goſpell. The Diſciples received the holy Spirit when they were firſt called, and after when Chriſt breathed on them, and ſaid, <hi>Receive the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Ioh. 20.22. but not in that meaſure that they did in the day of Pentecoſt, when the Spirit came downe upon them in a viſible ſhape. Before they had only taſted of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Act. 2.4.</note> but then they are ſaid to be <hi>filled with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost. Eadem ſemper fuit virtus chariſmatum, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2516:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>non eadem ſemper menſura donorum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo:</hi> The day of Pentecoſt was not the firſt time they had received the holy Ghoſt, <hi>non fuit inchoatio muneris, ſed adjectio largitatis,</hi> ſaith the ſame <hi>Leo:</hi> but yet in reſpect of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the Spirit, which was powred out on this day, they are formerly ſaid, not to have received the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And well may this day be called the feaſt of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending of the holy Ghoſt, becauſe the holy Ghoſt did never come downe in ſuch a meaſure, nor in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as upon this day. Thirdly, God is ſaid to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable in his actions, becauſe when he beginneth a good worke he never leaves it, till he bring it to an end. Whom hee elected, them he calleth; whom hee called, them he iuſtifieth; whom he iuſtified, them he ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; whom he ſanctified, them he glorifieth: <hi>For the gifts and calling of God are without repentance,</hi> Rom. 11.29 This ſerves mightily to confirme us in the certainety of our ſalvation: for howſoever we be changeable, &amp; readie to fall away from God at everie occaſion; yet God is one and the ſame, and doth alwayes perfect the good worke which he hath begun: and we keepe not him, but he keepeth us. <hi>Becauſe I am not changed, therefore yee are not conſumed, O yee ſonnes of Iacob,</hi> Mal. 3.6. So you ſee, that whether you conſider God in his nature, or in his decrees, or in his actions; it is alwayes true that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>With him there is no variableneſſe, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhadow of turning.</hi> Iam. 1.17.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by this that God is one, hee will ſignifie that he is without all reſpect of perſons; one and alike to all. In this ſenſe God is called one, <hi>Rom. 3.29.30.</hi> God: <hi>Is he the God of the Iewes onely, and not of the Gentiles alſo? yes even of the Gentiles alſo. For it is one God who ſhall justifie circumciſion of faith, and uncircumciſion through faith.</hi> And this is the intent of the Apoſtle in this place: for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2516:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe words are an argument to confirme his exhortation ſet downe in the beginning of the chapter; where the Apoſtle requires, that without limitation, wee pray and give thankes for all men. To ſtirre us up to the practiſe hereof, hee propounds unto us the pleaſure and will of God, verſ. 3.4. and next, the dealing of God &amp; of Chriſt, and their equall reſpect unto all, verſ. 5. <hi>There is one God and one Mediator.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay: God is one to all, both to Iewes and Gentiles, and all ſorts of men, ſo is the Mediator one and alike to all men. and therefore ſhould we carrie our ſelves equally towards all, ſecluding none from the benefite of our prayers.</p>
            <p>Now that ye may perceive how God is one and alike to all, we will conſider him in a foure-fold reſpect, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diverſe perſons which he carrieth, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which he worketh. Some things hee doth as a free Lord, having power over all: ſome things as God, creator and conſerver of all things: and ſome things hee worketh, as the God of his owne people onely, the father of his children: and other things, as hee is the Iudge of the whole world. As Lord of all, when all were ſinners guiltie before him, he ordained ſome for life, others for deſtruction: he loved <hi>Iacob,</hi> he hated <hi>Eſau:</hi> he hath mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on whom he will, and whom hee will hee hardneth: ſome he maketh veſſels of mercie, and others veſſels of wrath: ſome he calleth, but draweth not: others he both calleth and draweth, and others hee neither calleth nor draweth; and yet in ſo doing, hee is without all reſpect of perſons, one and alike to all. For hee is a reſpecter of perſons, who in iudgement, contrarie to law, diſtributes unto equals unequally, that which is equally due unto them: or hee who gives not alike unto equalls, when of right he is bound to give them alike; but ſo gratifyeth the one, that he wrongeth the other, and that for ſome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2516:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>outward condition in the partie, beſides the iuſtice of his cauſe, as either for his kinred, or his country, or carnall propinquitie, or his dignitie, or his riches, or ſome other office he hath done, and ſuch like externall qualities, by which men in iudgement are moved to favour one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie more than another. Now God electing one, reiecting another, while all were alike, even ſinners in <hi>Adam,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be guiltie of this: firſt, becauſe the mercie he ſhewes unto ſome, is not debt, but a gift of his free grace. and it is <hi>Austins</hi> rule, <hi>Ibi eſſe acceptionem perſonaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ubi quae aequalibus ex aequo debentur, inaequaliter distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur.</hi> But where the things given are not due, but free gifts; there, albeit there be not an equall diſtribution to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them who in themſelves are equall, yet it is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, nor anie iniuſtice at all. S. <hi>Austin</hi> clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this reaſon by two examples: the firſt is of a man that hath two debtors, and forgives the one, but exacts it of the other. This is not reſpect of perſons, becauſe hee is not bound to forgive either of them; and forgiving the one out of his owne good will, he wrongeth not the other: for he is free to diſpence his owne gifts as he will. Heare S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his owne words: <hi>Si autem quiſpiam duos habeat debitores, &amp; alteri vellet dimittere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad dua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſt. Pelagian. l. 2. cap 7.</note> 
               <hi>ab altero exigere, cui vult donat, ſed neminem fraudat, nec acceptio perſonarum dicenda est, quando iniquitas nulla est.</hi> His ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond inſtance is of the Houſholder in the Goſpell, who paying labourers who had wrought in his Vineyard,<note place="margin">Matth. 20.</note> gave as much unto them that had wrought but one houre, as unto them that had borne the burden and heate of the day: and when they murmured againſt him for his partialitie, he anſwered, and ſaid; <hi>Friend, I doe thee no wrong: diddest thou not agree with mee for a pennie?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſes 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Take that thine is, and goe thy way; I will give unto this last even as unto thee. Is it not lawfull for me to doe what I will with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2516:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>mine owne?</hi> On which words, S. <hi>Austin</hi> doth paraphraſe after this maner: <hi>Volo autem huic dare ſicut &amp; tibi, &amp;c. nempe hic totae justitia est: hoc volo: tibi inquit reddidi; huic donavi: neque ut huic darem, tibi aliquid abſtuli, aut quod debebam vel minui, vel negavi, &amp;c.</hi> The ſumme is: He freeth himſelfe from iniuſtice, for that unto them all he had given as much as hee was bound to give; and to ſome he had given more than he was bound: wherein he was gratious unto them, but not uniuſt towards the others; for that it is lawfull for him to doe what he will with his owne. Hence S. <hi>Austin</hi> inferreth, That as there was no acception of perſons in this man, diſtributing his owne favour unequally: ſo neither in God, electing one, reiecting another, while all were alike; for his election is no debt, but a gift of his free grace, which he may beſtow as he pleaſeth, either on all, or on none, or on ſome, and not on others. As the one have cauſe to extoll his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſo the other cannot accuſe his iuſtice: for hee might have paſt by them all, and appointed them for damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all being guiltie. And therefore that he hath mercie on ſome, he is freely good; becauſe he gives that which he is not bound to give: that he paſſeth by others, he is not uniuſt; becauſe he oweth them nothing: finally, that he condemneth thoſe whom he reiected for their ſinnes, he is iuſt; becauſe he payeth them that which hee oweth. This is the firſt reaſon, why God electing one, reiecting another, while all were alike, cannot be ſaid to be a reſpecter of perſons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for further cleering of Gods iuſtice, let us conſider that God electeth ſome, reiecteth others, <hi>citra cujuſquam injuriam:</hi> for, as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sic alius gratis honoratur, ut alius debito non fraudetur.</hi> though ſome be bountifully rewarded, yet others are not wronged. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a Iudge in iudgement, favouring one more than his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2516:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſe deſerveth; by how much hee gratifieth the one partie, by as much he damnifieth the other: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is a reſpecter of perſons. But though God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſome ſo farre, that whereas they deſerve damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he calleth them unto ſalvation, yet the reſt fare not the worſe for this: the glory of the elect addeth nothing to the paine of the reprobate; the wicked receive their owne meaſure, neither more not leſſe than they ſhould have done though none had beene ſaved. Finally, God electing ſome, and reiecting others, is free from reſpect of perſons; becauſe he is not moved to favour the one more than the other, by anie cauſe or condition in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but meerely by his owne good will and pleaſure. And it is well obſerved by ſome, that when it is ſaid in Scripture, that God is no reſpecter of perſons; the word <hi>perſona,</hi> ſignifieth not the man himſelfe, but ſome exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall qualitie, which being conſidered, might procure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, eyther favour or hatred: as beautie or deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nobilitie or baſeneſſe, riches or poverty, and ſuch like. Theſe outward qualities God doth no wayes reſpect in men: he regardeth not mens riches more than their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertie, <hi>Iam. 2.</hi> nor their freedome more than their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, <hi>Col. 3.11.</hi> neyther doth hee ſo diſtinguiſh betweene the Iew and the Grecian, that only for reſpect of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he embraceth the one, and reiecteth the other, <hi>Act. 10.34.</hi> but of everie nation, of all ſorts and conditions of men, he chooſeth ſome. So that if yee conſider God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this reſpect, as an abſolute Lord, uſing his libertie over his creatures, wherein he ſeemeth moſt partiall unto carnall minded men; yet yee ſee that he is without all reſpect of perſons, one and alike unto all.</p>
            <p>Next, God may be conſidered as the God of all: in which reſpect he created all things, conſerveth all things, doth good unto all; but with great difference and inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2516:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>for though he have made all things good, yet their eſſentiall goodneſſe doth not exclude an inequalitie of degrees, which was ſo requiſite for the perfection and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of this Univerſe: for <hi>in a great houſe are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly veſſels of gold and ſilver, but alſo of vvood and of earth, 2. Tim. 2.20.</hi> The Potter, albeit of the ſame lump of clay, yet muſt not make all his veſſels the ſame, but ſome for honeſt uſes, ſome for baſer imployments, becauſe men ſtand in need of both: ſo God, albeit he have made all things good, and given unto them all powers fitting the condition of their natures, and ſufficient for their owne ends and operations, yet he hath made ſome of a farte more noble condition than others; for unto ſome things he hath given only beeing, unto other things bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and life, unto others beeing, life and ſenſe, and unto others beeing, life, ſenſe, and reaſon, yea and a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall light to ſee manie things that cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by naturall reaſon. ſo that there is great difference <hi>inter Vermiculos in coeno, &amp; Angelos in coelo.</hi> And as there is inequalitie to be ſeene in the creation, ſo alſo in the preſervation: for though Gods providence bee exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto all things, even unto the Fowles of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Matth. 6.26.</hi> to the graſſe of the field, <hi>ver. 30.</hi> to the hayres of our head, <hi>Matth. 10.30.</hi> yet he hath greater care of ſome things than of other. By how much the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture commeth nearer unto God, by ſo much the higher place it hath in the order of his providence: ſo ſaith Chriſt, that God hath a greater care of men, than of Fowles,<note place="margin">Matt. 6.26. &amp;c.</note> or of Lillies. And there is good reaſon for it; for it is only for mans ſake, that God hath care of theſe things: for his ſake they were made, for his ſake it is that they are continued; and therfore God much more muſt have a care of man himſelfe. But albeit Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be not extended in like meaſure to all his creatures,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2516:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet is he not a reſpecter of perſons; becauſe (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) his gifts are no debt, but free grace, and he doth not wrong anie of his creatures. And laſtly, he is not moved to be more bountifull to ſome than to others, by anie cauſe and condition in themſelves, but meerely by his owne good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>There is a third conſideration of God, as he is the God of his owne people, the Father of his children, the Saviour of his bodie, the Head and Husband of his Church: and in this reſpect Gods actions doe reſpect onely thoſe that are of his owne family. He hath not done ſo unto everie nation, as he hath done unto them: for he begetteth them, he ſaveth them, he ruleth them, he quickneth them. But howſoever Gods ſpeciall love and favour be extended unto them all; yet here alſo wee muſt acknowledge an inequalitie. It is true, that God communicates ſpirituall life to all his members indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, inſomuch as the leaſt is a member of his bodie ſo well as the greateſt: &amp; in this reſpect all parts are peeres. But yet there are diverſe functions, diverſe gifts, diverſe meaſures of gifts, and ſo by conſequence for faſhion, and function, and imparitie. Firſt, I ſay, there are diverſe functions: for <hi>as wee have many members in one body, and all members have not the ſame office, Rom. 12.4.</hi> ſo it is with the myſticall bodie of Chriſt; there are manie members, and all have not the ſame office: but ſome are as the head, ſome as the eyes, others as the hands,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.21.</note> others as the feet. Chriſt aſcending on high, gave <hi>ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangelists, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, Epheſ. 4.11.</hi> Againe, there are diverſe gifts, namely extraordinarie gifts, which are not neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in everie one to ſalvation, as the gift of propheſie and diſcerning of ſpirits, the gifts of miracles, of tongues, and of interpretation of tongues. Of theſe, and ſuch like
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2516:12"/>ſaith the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12 ver. 4.8.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>There are diverſities of gifts, but the ſame ſpirit. To one is given by the Spirit the word of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to another the word of knowledge, to another the gifts of healing, &amp;c.</hi> the like is, <hi>Rom. 12.6.</hi> Finally, there are diverſe meaſures of ſaving graces, and of ſuch gifts as are abſolutely neceſſarie to ſalvation: for all have not the ſame meaſure of knowledge, but ſome are babes, and ſome are men of full age: all have not the ſame meaſure of faith; for Chriſt mentioneth a great faith, and a little faith: all have not the ſame meaſure of ſanctification; for ſome are termed perfect in reſpect of others: laſtly, neyther ſhall all have the ſame meaſure of glorie, but ſome ſhall ſhine as the Sunne, and others as the Starres in the firmament. But notwithſtanding this diverſitie of gifts that God beſtoweth upon his children, hee cannot be ſaid to be a reſpecter of perſons, for the ſame reaſons that are formerly alledged. And beſides, it was fit it ſhould be ſo, for manie reaſons: as that everie one might ſtand in need of anothers helpe; <hi>The eye cannot ſay unto the hand, I have no need of thee: nor againe the head to the feete I have no need of you, 1. Cor. 12.21.</hi> and eſpecially, that by this diverſitie, the beautie of the whole bodie might be ſet forth: <hi>Tota pulchra es amica mea:</hi> Chriſts myſticall bodie is all faire.<note place="margin">Can 4.7.</note> Now beautie conſiſteth in varietie of colours, and in a concine diſpoſition of ſundry different parts. <hi>If all the whole body were an eye, where were the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring? if the whole were hearing, where were the ſmelling? 1. Cor. 12.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, if yee conſider God as the Iudge of the whole world, his actions are to give ſentence and iudgement upon his creatures, not the ſame ſentence upon all, but the ſentence of abſolution unto ſome, the ſentence of condemnation againſt others: betweene which two, there is as great difference as betwixt life and death, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2516:12"/>yet no inequalitie, farre leſſe anie reſpect of perſons. In the three former conſiderations, God did not alwayes give alike to them, who in themſelves were equall; but here there is ever an equall diſtribution towards them, who in themſelves are alike: neither are anie diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in their recompence, that were not different in their lives. He obſerveth the rule of diſtributive iuſtice, which is, <hi>ſuum cuique tribuere;</hi> for, as the Scripture ſaith in manie places,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.10. Pſal. 62.18. Matth. 16.27. Rom 2 6. Rev. 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>He rewardeth every man according to his vvorkes.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth not the merit, but the meaſure and the rule by which the undeſerved rewards ſhall be diſtributed, and the deſerved puniſhments ſhall be inflicted. So it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in other places; as <hi>Matth. 9.29. According to your faith, be it unto you.</hi> and <hi>Matth. 23.3. After their workes,</hi> or, <hi>According to their workes, doe not.</hi> And ſo it muſt ſignifie in theſe places, where it is ſaid that God will reward eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man according to his workes: for <hi>Revel. 22.12.</hi> this phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is expounded to be, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>My reward is with me, to give everie man according as his worke ſhall be.</hi> that is, according as the qualitie of it ſhall be, whether good or bad; and alſo according as the quantity of it ſhall be, both for weight and number, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great or ſmall, manie or few: for God is ſo iuſt and unpartiall in his iudgements, that he hath reſpect both to the qualitie and to the quantitie of our worke, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly doth apportion a proportionable reward unto them. Firſt, the qualitie of everie mans workes ſhall be tryed, whether they be good or bad, and their reward will be divided accordingly. <hi>It ſhall be well with the just, for they ſhall eate the fruit of their workes: and wo to the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, it ſhall be evill with him, for the reward of his hands ſhall be given him,</hi> Eſai 3.10. <hi>He will render to everie man according to his deeds.—Tribulation and anguiſh upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2516:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſoule of man that doth evill, of the lew first, and alſo of the Gentile. But glory, honour, and peace to everie man that worketh good, &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 2.6.9.10.11. <hi>For we muſt all appear before the judgement ſeate of Christ, that every man may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, vvhether it be good or bad,</hi> 2. Cor. 5.10. <hi>They ſhall come forth that have done good, unto the reſurrection of life, but they that have done evill, unto the reſurrection of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi> Ioh. 5.29. Againe, the quantitie of everie mans workes ſhall be tryed, both their number and their weight, and the meaſure of reward proportioned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. For the number, hee keepeth an exact record and inventorie of all our workes: hee hath a bottle for our teares, <hi>Pſal. 56.8.</hi> a bagge for our almes, <hi>Luk. 12.33.</hi> and a booke for our good workes, as alſo for the ſinnes of the wicked. <hi>Dan. 7.10. The judgement was ſet, and the bookes opened. Revel. 20.12. The bookes are opened, and the dead are judged of thoſe things which are written in the bookes.</hi> Theſe bookes are two; <hi>libriſcientiae Dei,</hi> and <hi>conſcientiae nostrae,</hi> the lieger booke of Gods knowledge, and the count booke of our owne conſcience: wherein both the good workes of the godly, and the ſinnes of the wicked, are ſo particularly written, that not anie of our good workes ſhall be forgotten, <hi>Heb. 6.10.</hi> nor yet anie of the ſinnes of the wicked; not ſo much as an idle word, but they ſhall give account thereof in the day of iudgement, <hi>Matth. 12.36.</hi> And as the number of our workes, ſo alſo the weight ſhall be ſcanned: for he commeth with a bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance in his hand, and in this ballance of iuſtice, will hee poize, both the goodneſſe of mens workes and the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſneſſe of their ſinnes. Now from this difference, both of the ſinnes of the wicked, and of the good workes of the godly, in their number and weight, ſhall ariſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent degrees, both of puniſhments in hell, and of ioyes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2516:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>in heaven. According to the number of mens ſinnes, ſhall be the number of their paines: <hi>Revel. 18.7. As much as ſhe lived in pleaſures, ſo much give you to her torment and ſorrow.</hi> and according to the grievouſneſſe of their ſinnes, ſhall be the greatneſſe of their puniſhment. It ſhall be eaſier for <hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> than for <hi>Corazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, Luk. 10.14.</hi> He that ſinneth of ignorance ſhall be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with fewer ſtripes, than hee who ſinneth of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Luk. 12.47.48.</hi> The like may be ſaid of the ioyes of heaven: though all ſhall receive fulneſſe of ioy, yet there ſhall be ſeverall degrees of ioy, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall degrees of preſent grace, by which they are diverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly capable of future glorie. Hee that hath done manie good workes, ſhall receive manie rewards; <hi>for God is not unrighteous, that hee ſhould forget anie of our good workes, Heb. 6.10.</hi> No, not a cup of cold water ſhall ſlip unrewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Matth. 10.42. Hee that ſoweth plenteouſly, ſhall reape plenteouſly, 2. Cor. 9.6.</hi> And a weightier good done, hath a weightier reward given: <hi>Thou ſhalt rest &amp; ſtand up in thy lot at the end of the dayes,</hi> ſaid the Angell to <hi>Daniel, Dan. 12.13.</hi> There is one general lot, for all them that be wiſe, to ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament: but they that turne manie to righteouſneſſe, have a ſpeciall lot, to <hi>ſhine as the ſtarres for ever and ever, Dan. 12.3.</hi> So that, albeit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happineſſe be due only by promiſe, as a portion of grace, yet it is duely performed by proportion of iuſtice. God uſeth an equall inequalitie: <hi>for every one ſhall receive his owne reward according to his owne labour, 1. Cor. 3.8.</hi> So that God everie way is both iuſt and unpartiall. Thus have I ſhewed, that in what reſpect ſoever wee conſider God, he is without all reſpect of perſons, one and alike to all: <hi>There is one God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third thing we have to ſpeake of, is, that God is made one with us by a Mediator: for <hi>there is a Mediator
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2516:14"/>betweene God and man.</hi> A mediator is a middle perſon, that commeth betweene two parties that be at variance, to be a meane of attonement and peace; who dealeth with each partie, untill he bring them under ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and covenant. Now it is plaine, that God and man were at enmitie; man the partie offending, God the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie offended: a middle perſon commeth in between, and labours a reconciliation, binding up a covenant between them, That man ſhal ſatisfie for the wrong he hath done, and performe obedience in times comming; as alſo on the other part, That God ſhall remit his wrath, receive man into his favour, and give unto him eternall life. But becauſe man was unable to performe his part of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, this ſame Mediator becommeth his ſuertie, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaketh for him, both to ſatisfie the law and iuſtice of God for mans ſinne, and alſo to make him performe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in time following, by renewing him againe unto the image, which he had loſt in <hi>Adam.</hi> That hee might performe the firſt, hee behoved to be a Prieſt, to offer up himſelfe in an expiatorie ſacrifice: and that hee might performe the ſecond, it was needful that he ſhould be a Prophet and a King. for the corruption of man, which he was to take away, that man might performe obedience to God, had two parts; ignorance in the mind, and enormitie or rebellion in the will and affections. To cure our ignorance, hee behoved to be a Prophet to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us: to take away our enormitie and rebellion, hee muſt be a King, powerfully to convert our hearts, and to rule the ſame by his ſpirit; that ſo hee might make us to obey God all the reſt of our life, wee being once made partakers of his ſatisfaction. So our Mediator being our ſuertie, was both a Prieſt, a Prophet and a King: a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchizedeck, Pſal. 110.4.</hi> a Prophet, to be heard when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould hold his peace, <hi>Deut. 18.18.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2516:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>a King, to ſave his people, whoſe name ſhould be the <hi>Lord our righteouſneſſe,</hi> Ier. 23.6. <hi>Davids</hi> Prieſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> his Prophet, <hi>Ieremies</hi> King. and theſe formerly had met double, two of them in ſome other; <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> King and Prieſt; <hi>Samuel,</hi> Prieſt and Prophet; <hi>David,</hi> Prophet and King: never all three, but in him alone.</p>
            <p>As he who is Mediator betweene God and man, is ſuertie for man performing his part: ſo alſo doth he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme Gods part to man. He who as Mediator, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Suertie, ſatisfied for ſinne, doth, as he is God, remit that ſinne which he ſatisfied for, receive man into his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, give him grace in this life, and glory in the life to come; and, in a word, performes all Gods part of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. For this cauſe the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the covenant, in reſpect of Gods part, <hi>Christs Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> becauſe Chriſt hath bequeathed thoſe things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us in his legacie, namely, remiſsion of ſinnes, iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and eternall life. So that we have a double benefite by the death of our Mediator: one, that thereby he hath ſatisfied for our ſinnes, as he is our Suertie: another, that thereby he hath confirmed his Teſtament, contayning a diſpoſition of theſe things, which God hath bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by covenant to give us; <hi>For a Testament is of no ſtrength while the Testator liveth, Heb. 9.16.</hi> Thus after a wonderfull maner, one is both Mediator to draw on an agreement betweene theſe two parties, and ſuertie for mans part of the bargaine; and alſo he performeth Gods part of the covenant, bequeathing unto us in legacie theſe things which God hath promiſed to give us, and as a faithfull teſtator confirming the ſame by his death.</p>
            <p>Then God is reconciled to man by a mediator: but have the Angels no benefite by his mediation, ſeeing the Apoſtle only ſaith that there is a mediator between God and man? I anſwer; that they have, though not ſo great
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2516:15"/>as man:
<list>
                  <item>1. They have this benefite, that they are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and united under one head together with the reſt of the Church; for all things, both which are in heaven, and which are in earth, are gathered together in one, in Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ. 1.10.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. They have this benefite alſo, that their friendſhip with man is renued, he being reconciled to God.</item>
                  <item>3. By this mediator their ruins are repaired, and their number filled: becauſe men that are reconciled, ſucceed in the place of Angels that fell, ſaith S. <hi>Austin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. He furniſheth unto them matter of ioy; for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at the converſion of a ſinner.</item>
                  <item>5. By him they get greater knowledge of the myſteries of God revealed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</item>
                  <item>6. By him they are confirmed ſo in grace that they cannot fall, they being changeable of themſelves: therefore we ſay in the Schooles, That though they have not a mediator of redemption, yet they have a mediator of confirmation.</item>
               </list> according to that of <hi>Bernard: Qui ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit hominem lapſum, dedit ſtanti Angelo ne laberetur: ſic illum de captivitate eruens, ſicut hunc à captivitate defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</hi> Finally, ſome ſay they have this benefite alſo, that their obedience being not perfect enough of it ſelfe, nor able to ſtand before God; <hi>for he findeth iniquity in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels:</hi> is accepted as moſt perfect for this mediators ſake. and therefore they are ſaid even to be reconciled to God by this mediatour, <hi>Col. 1.20.</hi> Others goe further, ſaying, that the Angels, as alſo all other creatures, beſides man, had declined ſomewhat from their firſt beginning; but were reſtored againe to their integritie by this mediator. and ſo they underſtand the word <hi>recapitulat, Eph. 1.10.</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth to call a thing backe to the firſt beginning, as well as to gather in one head; as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth both the head, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a thing.</p>
            <p>The fourth point ſet downe here, is, that this media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2516:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>is one; <hi>There is one Mediator.</hi> Whereby, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the one God, three things are ſignified: that he is indiviſible, immutable, and alike to all. 1. He is one, that is, indiviſible, one onely, not manie; and that both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his perſon, and in reſpect of his office. His per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is indiviſible and onely one: for albeit he be God and man, yet he is not two, but one. <hi>Non alter ex patre, alter ex matre; ſed aliter ex patre, aliter ex matre,</hi> as was concluded againſt the wicked hereſie of <hi>Nestorius</hi> Biſhop of Conſtantinople, who divided the two natures of our mediator, making them two perſons. He was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the third generall Councell at Epheſus, where it was decreed that the bleſſed Virgin was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, becauſe there was but one perſon, that was both God begotten of the Father, and man borne of his mother. and in the Councell of Chalcedon, which was the fourth generall, to ſhew that his perſon was but one, againſt <hi>Nestorius,</hi> they uſed two adverbes, ſaying that his natures were united <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without diviſion, without ſeparation: which the Fathers expreſſe by ſundry ſimilitudes. <hi>Iustin</hi> uſeth the ſimilitude of the ſoule and the bodie, which are ſo united that they make but one perſon. <hi>Damaſcen</hi> the ſimilitude of an hote iron, which being but one thing ſubſiſting, hath in it two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct natures, the fire and the iron; everie one whereof, hath his ſeverall action concurring to one worke: the heate burneth, the iron cutteth. Even ſo the mediator being one perſon, hath two diſtinct natures, everie one whereof hath his ſeverall action, concurring to the work of mediation. But the moſt ſignificant ſimilitude is that of a Vine tree, and a bough graffed into the Vine: for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as that bough hath no being or ſubſiſtence of it ſelfe, but both groweth and liveth in the ſtocke of the Vine; ſo the humane nature of our mediator, having no ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2516:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of it ſelfe, is, as it were, ingraffed into the perſon of the Sonne, who is the true Vine, and is wholly ſupported and ſuſteined by it. therefore there be not two perſons, but one; the humane nature being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, void of all perſonalitie or ſubſiſtence, and aſſumed by the Sonne of God, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a perſon ſubſiſting of himſelfe and by himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Againe, as his perſon, ſo likewiſe his office is indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: for <hi>he received an unchangeable Priesthood,</hi> which cannot paſſe from him unto any other, <hi>Heb. 7.24.</hi> So that beſides him, there is no other mediator, neyther can be. For in a true and ſufficient mediator there muſt be foure properties, which are not to be found in anie but him:
<list>
                  <item>1. The word of God muſt reveale and propound him to the Church, that in conſcience wee may be aſſured, that praying to God in his name, we ſhall be heard: but there is no Scripture that mentioneth anie other mediator but onely one.</item>
                  <item>2. Hee that is mediator betweene God and man, muſt partake of both natures: for <hi>a Mediator is not of one, Gal. 3.20.</hi> So then he that is Mediator betweene God &amp; man muſt not be of one nature, he muſt be both God and man: hee muſt be God, that hee may ſpeake to God for us: he muſt be man, that hee may ſpeake from God to man. <hi>Mediatorem inter nos &amp; Deum</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Austin</hi>) <hi>&amp; mortalitatem habere opportuit tranſeuntem, &amp; beatitatem permanentem.</hi> but there is only one that is both God and man.</item>
                  <item>3. A mediatour muſt be perfectly iuſt: <hi>for ſuch an high Priest became us, who is holy, blameleſſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, ſeparate from ſinners, and made higher than the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Heb. 7.26.</hi> As the Apoſtle ſhewes that they could not be high Prieſts, who had need to offer for their owne ſinnes, as well as for the ſinnes of the people, <hi>Heb. 7.27.</hi> ſo they cannot be mediators, who had need of a mediator for themſelves. Now none is perfectly iuſt but onely
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2516:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>one. The Saints in heaven, howſoever they be fully iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, ſanctified, glorified, yet in themſelves they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and therefore muſt needs ſtand before God by the mediation of another: So that S. <hi>Austin</hi> reaſoneth well, that he is the only true mediator, <hi>pro quo nullus interpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat, ſed ipſe pro omnibus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. A mediator muſt be a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiator, that is, bring ſomething to God that may ſatisfie his iuſtice for our ſinnes: therefore S. <hi>Iohn</hi> having told us, that we have an advocate with the Father, he addeth, <hi>and he is a propitiation for our ſinnes, 1. Ioh. 2.2.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> But there is none other that is a propitiation for our ſinnes; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore but one Mediator.</p>
            <p>But the Papiſts thinke to eſcape this by a rotten diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of mediators of redemption, &amp; interceſsion. There is but one mediator of redemption (ſay they) but manie mediators of interceſsion, even all the Saints in heaven. Whereunto I ſay,
<list>
                  <item>1. That theſe foure properties are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially required in an advocate and mediatour of interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, rather then in a redeemer: but they are not to bee found in anie but in one.</item>
                  <item>2. The Apoſtle here affirming that there is one mediator, meaneth rather a mediator of interceſsion: for throughout this whole chapter hee is ſpeaking of prayers and interceſsions.</item>
                  <item>3. And this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction is idle; becauſe none can bee an advocate or mediator of interceſsion, but he that is our redeemer: for the word (Advocate) is borrowed of Lawyers and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth him onely that doth pleade the iuſtice of his clients cauſe. A ſtranger in the Court, may become a petitioner to the Iudge, and entreate favour for the guiltie perſon: but advocates are Proctors and patrons of their clyents; therefore he alone is our advocate, who being our redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, can pleade his iuſtice beſtowed upon us. and Saints, though they be petitioners to God in our behalfe, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they redeemed us not, they cannot be our advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2516:17"/>to pleade the iuſtice of our cauſe. It is ſure that Miniſters pray for the people, and that <hi>ex efficio:</hi> yet S. <hi>Augustin</hi> reproveth <hi>Parmonian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 2. cont. ep. Parm. c. 8.</note> for placing the Biſhop mediator betweene God and the people.</item>
                  <item>4. The Saints do not ſo much as intercede for us, namely, particularly: for it is as impoſsible for them to be interceſſors, as redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</item>
               </list>
for he who is an interceſſor for us, muſt heare our prayers, know what things we ſtand in need of, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand our verie ſecret wants and groanes: But this none but God can doe, as <hi>Salomon</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>1. King. 8.39. Thou only knowest the heart.</hi> and <hi>Eccles. 9.5. The dead know nothing at all.</hi> Therefore is it ſaid of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that he was taken away by death, that he might not ſee the evill that was to come; which cannot be true, if ſo be that <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> being a Saint in heaven, did ſee and know the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars that were done upon the earth. Finally, this the Church doth acknowledge unto God, <hi>Eſa. 03.16. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham is Ignorant of us, and Iacob knoweth us not.</hi> Upon which place, S. <hi>Austin</hi> reaſoneth verie well: <hi>If ſo great Patriarches were Ignorant what became of the people which were borne of their loynes: how is it like that other dead can be preſent, to understand mens affaires?</hi> Laſtly, this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction is overthrowne by themſelves: for they make Saints mediators of redemption, as well as of interceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Aquinas</hi> doth avow,<note place="margin">a. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. q 83. ar. 4.</note> that our prayers are effectuall by the merits of Saints. And yee know what is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of their whole Church for humane ſatisfactions, namely, <hi>paſsionibus ſanctorum expiari delicta,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Bellar de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgen. l. 1. c. 2.</note> which is a blaſphemie worthie the tearing of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Thus they ſometimes make Saints mediators of redemption, ſometimes they denie it, and ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict both themſelves &amp; the Apoſtle here, affirming that our mediator is one.</p>
            <p>As hereby heſignifieth that the mediator is one only,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2516:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>not manie: ſo likewiſe that hee is immutable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, one and the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever. So ſaith the author of the booke of Wiſedome, ſpeaking of this Mediator, that uncreated Wiſedome: <hi>Being one, ſhe can doe all things.</hi> And the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb. 1.12.</hi> applyeth that place of the Pſalme to him; <hi>Thou art the ſame, and thy yeares ſhall not fayle.</hi> He is one and the ſame <hi>objectivé, ſubjectivé, effectivé: Objectivé,</hi> the ſame in his word; for he who yeſterday was ſhadowed in the Law, is to day ſhewed in the Goſpell. <hi>Idem ſubjectivé,</hi> the ſame in his perſon, and in his attributes and office: in his perſon, the ſame before and after his Incarnation; for taking upon him our nature, he was no more chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereby, than a man is by putting on a veſture. <hi>Homo quippe Deo acceſsit, non Deus á ſe receſsit; home factus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam ſuſcipiende nostram, non amittende ſuam.</hi> as the divine Poet verie ſweetly:</p>
            <q>Ille manet quod ſemper erat, quod non erat eſſe incipiens.</q>
            <p>He did not leave off to be what he was, but he begun to be what he was not. Againe, he is the ſame in his attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, in his power, in his office; being alwayes the Lord of his people, the ſhepheard of his flocke, the head of his Church, the mediator betweene God and man. Finally, he is <hi>idem effectivé,</hi> the ſame in his workes, in his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in his grace: he who yeſterday was a mediator for <hi>Abraham, Izaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> is to day a mediator for us: he is as well now the light of the Gentiles, as he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the glory of his people Iſraell.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, by this that he is one, is ſignified that he is without all reſpect of perſons, one and alike to all; not the mediator of the Iewes onely, but of the Gentiles alſo. <hi>There is neyther Iew nor Greeke, there is neyther bond nor free, there is neither male nor female: for all are one in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2516:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Christ. Gal. 3.28. He is peace to him that is neere, and peace to him that is farre off, Eſa. 57.19.</hi> that is, as the Fathers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it, peace to the Iewes that are neere, and peace to the Gentiles that are farre off. This one bleſſed peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker hath made attonement for both, and appeareth daily in the ſight of God to pleade our pardon, as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Advocate and high Prieſt. S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, that his armes were ſtretched out upon the croſſe, to ſignifie this, That hee was now to embrace, not an handfull of people, as he did before the nation of the Iewes; but as manie as his armes were able to containe: that now hee was to breake downe that partition wall, which for a long time had bene between Iewes and Gentiles, and become one to all. <hi>There is one Mediator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as yet we know not who is this one Mediator: therefore leſt the Iewes ſhould ſay that it were their long looked for <hi>Meſsias;</hi> or the Turkes, their <hi>Mahomet;</hi> or the Friers, that it were S. <hi>Francis,</hi> or S. <hi>Dominick,</hi> or finally all Papiſts, who conſtrue it of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> for there is more mention of her in their prayers, than of Chriſt; and the propheticall Pſalmes of Chriſt are transferred unto <hi>Mary,</hi> and what elſe is magnifically ſpoken of him in Scripture, even the firſt promiſe that was made of this Mediator, <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> tranſlated as ſpoken of her in their moſt approved Bible, <hi>ipſa conteret caput tuum.</hi> although (as their owne Ieſuite <hi>Ribera</hi> confeſſeth) the Hebrew text, the Chaldee paraphraſe, the Septuagints tranſlation, and all good Latine copies reade <hi>ipſe conteret.</hi> For this cauſe the Apoſtle in the fift place, leades us, as it were by the hand, to the verie perſon, deſcribing him by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name, and ſurname: <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> he is this one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, who therefore is called the <hi>Angell of the Covenant, Mal. 3.1.</hi> and, <hi>the covenant of the people, Eſa. 49.8. the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of the new covenant, vvhoſe blood ſpeaketh better
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2516:18"/>things then the blood of Abel, Heb. 12.24. Our peace, Eph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14. The way and the doore by which we have acceſſe unto the Father, Ioh. 14.6. The way into the holiest of all, Heb. 9.8.</hi> finally, an <hi>high Priest</hi> who came by a more perfect Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, not made with hands; and who not by the blood of Goats and Calves, but <hi>by his owne blood entred in once into the holy place, having obtayned eternall redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for us, Heb. 9.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come to the laſt head, that Chriſt Ieſus is a man; <hi>The man Christ Ieſus. Homo verus,</hi> but not <hi>homo merus:</hi> he is a true man, as having
<list>
                  <item>1. the ſubſtance of a true body and ſoule:</item>
                  <item>2. the eſſentiall and naturall properties of ſoule and bodie:</item>
                  <item>3. the infirmities alſo, and ſuch defects as be naturall.</item>
               </list>
I ſay ſuch as be naturall, to exclude two ſorts of infirmities;
<list>
                  <item>1. theſe which doe not univerſally follow the nature of man, but are onely perſonall apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to ſome particular men, and ariſing from private cauſes, &amp; particular iudgements: as to be borne a foole, to be ſicke of an ague, conſumption, leproſie, and ſuch like diſeaſes.</item>
                  <item>2. Sinnes, which be infirmities indeed, but not naturall, but rather contrarie to nature;</item>
               </list>
becauſe they belong not to nature as it is whole, but as it is corrupt. Neither of theſe Chriſt tooke upon him; becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved him to be like man in generall, not like to this or that man in particular: againe, like unto man in generall in all things, except ſinne, <hi>Heb. 4.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It behoved Chriſt to be like unto us, a man as we are whether we conſider him as he was our Suertie, or as our high Prieſt, or as our Ranſome, or as our Redeemer, or as our Mediator, or finally, as he is our Phyſitian. In all theſe reſpects it behoved him to be a man.
<list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe he was our Suertie, to make ſatisfaction to God for our debt: and the iuſtice of God requires, that ſatisfaction be made in the ſame nature that finned.</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2516:19"/>high Prieſt: <hi>For every high Priest is ordeyned to offer gifts and ſacrifices; wherefore it is of neceſsity that this man alſo have ſomewhat to offer, Heb. 8.3.</hi> now if he had remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned God only, he ſhould not have had anie thing to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</item>
                  <item>3. Becauſe our Ranſome; for as hee was the high Prieſt, ſo he was the ſacrifice: he muſt offer up himſelfe for us. He was our ſuertie to ſatisfie for us, and his ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction behoved to be paſsive and penall, yea it muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſelfe unto death; <hi>for without ſhedding of blood there is no remiſsion, Heb. 9.22.</hi> but remayning God onely, hee could not have dyed.</item>
                  <item>4. Becauſe our Redeemer; for by the Law, he that redeemeth another, muſt be his brother or kinſman, one that hath the right of propinquitie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Levit. 25.48.</hi> and therefore the Hebrew word <hi>Goel,</hi> which ſignifieth a Redeemer, doth alſo ſignifie a Kinſman.</item>
                  <item>5. Becauſe our Mediator and Advocate; for, (as I ſaid before) <hi>a Mediator is not of one, Gal. 3.20.</hi> that is, he is not of one nature. But he that is mediator betweene God and man, muſt be both God and man: God, that he may ſpeake to God for us: man, that he may ſpeake to us from God.</item>
               </list>
Finally, hee muſt be man, becauſe our Phyſitian; for it was fit that our Phyſitian ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our conditions, and ſhould have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his owne perſon of our infirmities: that being tempted in like ſort as we are, he might be able to ſuccour us that are tempted, <hi>Heb. 2.17.</hi> So that Chriſt both is, and muſt have beene a man</p>
            <p>The conſideration hereof, ſerves us for conſolation. It is the key of all comfort: for all true comfort ſtands in happineſſe, all happineſſe is in fellowſhip with God; and never could there be ſo great fellowſhip with God, as this: for God hath entred in alliance with us, ſending his Sonne to be made of a woman, to become a man, and ſo our brother, even <hi>Emanuel,</hi> God with us, or in our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2516:19"/>fleſh. Hereby God comforted our firſt parents, when they were caſt downe with a ſight of their ſinnes, and a feare of puniſhment, <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> Hereby he comforted <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> by the viſion of a ladder reaching from heaven to earth: this ladder is the Sonne of God made man.<note place="margin">Iob 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> comforts himſelfe with this, that he had a redeemer in his owne fleſh. By this did <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Angell comfort <hi>Daniel, Dan. 9.21. &amp;c.</hi> and finally, by this doe the Angels comfort the Shepheard; <hi>Behold I bring you good tydings of great ioy, which ſhall be to all people: for unto you is borne this day in the city of David, a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord, Luk. 2.10.</hi> Yea this is that wherwith we muſt all be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted: for if Chriſt Ieſus be a man, then be ye well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he will be a mercifull high Prieſt, a favourable Iudge, a homely Mediator, to whom we may goe boldly as unto a brother of ours.</p>
            <p>This we are to hold faſt, it being the greateſt ground of all comfort; and the rather alſo, becauſe the Divell in all ages hath oppugned this doctrine, and eyther in whole or in part, laboured to obſcure the veritie of Chriſts humane nature, and to bereave us of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that Chriſt Ieſus is a man. Firſt, he raiſed up ſome immediatly after the Apoſtles dayes, who taught that Chriſt was not a true man, but onely in ſhew, having a phantaſticall bodie: againſt whom <hi>Ignatius</hi> did write. Theſe were firſt one <hi>Cerdon,</hi> after him <hi>Marcion,</hi> whom <hi>Polycarpus</hi> called <hi>primogenitum Satanae,</hi> the Divels eldeſt ſonne. but ſince he hath had manie brethren: for a ſhort while after came the Manichees, maintaining the ſame. Secondly, but becauſe this was ſo notoriouſly falſe that it could not take place, Satan raiſed up others to mince and mitigate this blaſphemie, ſaying, that he had an humane bodie indeed, yet not like unto ours: not of the ſubſtance of the Virgin, but either of the ſubſtance of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2516:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>or of the matter of the heavens, or of the ſtarres, or finally, made of the elements, which paſſed through the womb of the Virgin, as water through a conduit-pipe. Theſe were the Valentinians, whoſe hereſie was renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of late by the Anabaptiſts. Thirdly, becauſe theſe could not prevaile, he raiſed up others, who taught, That howſoever hee had a true bodie, yet hee lacked a ſoule: theſe were the Arrians. Theſe were condemned in the Councell of Nice. Fourthly, and therefore Satan raiſed up others to fyne this hereſie better, ſaying, That he had the vegetative and ſenſitive part of the ſoule, but wanted the reaſonable part. This was <hi>Apolinaris</hi> Biſhop of Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea: he was condemned in a Synod holden at Rome, under Pope <hi>Damaſus.</hi> Fiftly, aroſe <hi>Eutyches</hi> Abbot of Conſtantinople, and taught, That howſoever before the union he had a perfect humane nature, yet after the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this humane nature was converted, conſumed, and ſwallowed up by his Godhead. He was condemned in the Councell of Chalcedon, where it was decreed, that the natures of Chriſt were united, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without change, and confuſion. Sixtly, but albeit hee was condemned, Satan left it not ſo, but raiſed up others, who propounded this hereſie in other termes; namely, <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> who maintained, That although his manhood was not conſumed of his Godhead by the union; yet of both mixed together, there was compounded a third na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And to make the ſame hereſie more plauſible yet, Satan ſent forth others to fyne and poliſh it better, to wit, the <hi>Acephali</hi> (ſo called, becauſe it was not knowne who was their head) affirming, That at leaſt the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of both natures were confounded; the properties of the manhood communicate to the Godhead, and the properties of the Godhead transfuſed into the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. This hereſie hath beene renewed in our age, firſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2516:20"/>by <hi>Hoffmannus</hi> an Anabaptiſt: then after by <hi>Schwencfel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius;</hi> and laſtly, by the Ubiquitaties, who falſly boaſt themſelves of the name of <hi>Luther.</hi> Seventhly, becauſe this way ſucceeded not, Satan went about another way to bereave us of Chriſts manhood: he ſent out <hi>Macarius</hi> Patriarch of Antiochia, and <hi>Honorius</hi> Biſhop of Rome, who taught, That Chriſt as hee was man wanted ſome part of his reaſonable ſoule, namely, a will; who for this cauſe were called <hi>Monotheletae.</hi> They were condemned in the ſixt generall Councell, which was the third hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at Conſtantinople. Eighthly, he ſtirred up others, whoſe doctrine was more plauſible, teaching, That hee had a perfect humane nature; yet could not properly be called a man, for the humane nature was aſſumed by him, onely as a man doth a veſture, by an accidentall, not by an eſſentiall union: againſt whom <hi>Damaſcen</hi> doth prove, that Chriſts natures were united <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. Ninthly, becauſe all theſe hereſies did oppugne the ſubſtance of Chriſts humanitie, in whole, or in part; or elſe the properties thereof, and ſo could not take place in the Church: therefore the Divell ſtirred up others, at leaſt to take away the infirmities of his manhood, theſe were the <hi>Aphthardokitae,</hi> teaching That Chriſts body was not ſubiect to anie paſsions. And albeit this was reſiſted when it came by them, yet Satan advanced his purpoſe mightily by ſome others, being otherwiſe good men and orthodox; who taught, That Chriſt had <hi>corpus ad patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſed non naturam ad dolendum.</hi> Finally, the laſt who have fought in this quarrell, under the Divels Banner, are the Papiſts. And they are moſt dangerous, becauſe they doe not directly denie his manhood: for then few would beleeve them; but by way of conſequence, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his bodie of the eſſentiall properties of a true bodie, while they teach, that his bodie is not viſible, nor ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2516:21"/>nor circumſcribed in one place: but an inviſible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, uncircumſcribed bodie, which is preſent, with all dimenſions, in ten thouſand places at once. This is as much as to ſay, that it is no bodie, nor Chriſt himſelfe a true man. Againſt all theſe hereſies, the verie naming of my Text is a ſufficient refutation, that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is a man.</p>
            <p>There be other hereſies on the other hand, which ſeem to accord better with my Text: as firſt, That Chriſt is not God, but onely man; which was the blaſphemie of <hi>Ebion, Cerinthus, Carpocrates, Photinus, Samoſatenus,</hi> and the reſt of that damnable crew. 2. That though he both be God and man, yet he is mediator only as man; which is the doctrine of the Papiſts Both claime this Text for a warrant and ground of their opinion: but in vaine. for the Apoſtle calls him not a man, to ſignifie that hee is a meere man; for that were contrarie to his own doctrine: nor yet doth he call him man, to ſhew that he is media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor only as man; for that were as contrarie to the truth: it being plaine, that Chriſt wrought the worke of media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to both natures, by a different act and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. And therefore <hi>Damaſcen</hi> learnedly diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foure things in the mediator:
<list>
                  <item>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the agent or worker, which is the perſon of Chriſt:</item>
                  <item>2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the beginning from which the action doth proceed, which is twofold; his divine, and his humane natures:</item>
                  <item>3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the action it ſelfe:</item>
                  <item>4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the externall worke of our redemption, called by <hi>Dyoniſius Areopagit.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>opus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe it doth proceed from him who is both God &amp; man. and to the effecting of it both the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with their diſtinct actions, in one and the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, did concurr: According to that of <hi>Leo,</hi> approved by the whole Councell of Chalcedon; <hi>Vtraque forma agit quod ſuum est, cum communione alterius, verbo (ſcilicet)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2516:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>agente quod verbi est, &amp; carne exequente quod carnis est.</hi> This he manifeſteth by examples: In his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſaith he) he wrought our ſalvation, by keeping of the Law, ſuffering and dying: in his divine nature, by giving ſtrength unto his manhood to endure death, and worth to his blood to be a ſufficient ſatisfaction. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Austin</hi> concludeth well: <hi>Non mediator homo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter divinitatem, divina humanitas, &amp; humana divinitas mediatrix.</hi> It is the divine humanitie, and humane divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, that is our mediator.</p>
            <p>But why then is he called a man? I anſwer, for manie reaſons:
<list>
                  <item>1. To inſinuate unto us a reaſon why he is one and alike to all; becauſe he took upon him the common nature of men: he is a man, alike neare to all that bee men.</item>
                  <item>2. To expreſſe the perfection of his mediatorſhip: he was our mediator from the beginning, but never a complete mediator till he became man; for there are manie workes of his mediatorſhip, which could not bee performed but in our nature.</item>
                  <item>3. To ſignifie the order by which wee are conioyned with God: We are ioyned to God by a mediator. and foraſmuch as this mediator is both God &amp; man, we are united firſt into his manhood, and thereby unto his Godhead. We muſt faſten the eyes of our faith firſt of all upon the fleſh of Chriſt, as it were upon the vaile by which the entrance was into the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſanctorum,</hi> where the glorie of God ſhined; and then after that, enter, as it were, into the Sanctuarie it ſelfe, to behold his Godhead.</item>
                  <item>4. Hee calleth him a man for our comfort.</item>
               </list>
There is a certaine baſeneſſe of an abiect mind, and ſlaviſh feare, which the Divell worketh in men; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them, that it were great boldneſſe to goe direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto Chriſt: as if he were of that auſteritie and ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe that earthly Princes are, and therefore wee muſt ſend the Saints unto him to ſolicite him in our behalfe.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2516:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>This is all the ground the Papiſts have for their invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints: but the Apoſtle calls it voluntarie or ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh humilitie, <hi>Col. 1.18.</hi> and here hee meeteth with it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, calling Chriſt a man: he is a man, and therefore as neare unto us, and hath as compaſsionate bowels as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Saint. Indeed if wee conſider Chriſt as he is God, dwelling in light unacceſsible, I know not what confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we can have to goe unto him: but when wee caſt our eyes below upon his manhood, how that he is like unto us in all things except ſinne, tempted in all ſort as we are, that he might be able to ſuccour us when wee are tempted,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.17, 18.</note> and ſuch a one as can be touched with the ſenſe of our infirmities;<note place="margin">&amp; 4.15, 16.</note> then (as ſaith the Apoſtle) wee may go <hi>boldly unto the throne of grace;</hi> we may caſt the anchor of our hope within the veyle:<note place="margin">&amp; 6.19, 20.</note> then may wee be bold to enter into the holieſt of all,<note place="margin">&amp; 10.19, 20.</note> through his blood, by the new and living way, which hee hath prepared for us, through the vaile, that is, his fleſh.</p>
            <p>I doubt not now but that theſe things have been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently cleared, by way of explication; That there is a God, That this God is one, That he is made one with us by a Mediator, That the Mediator is one, That this one Mediator is Chriſt Ieſus, That Chriſt Ieſus is a man. But as theſe things are ſufficiently cleared, ſo I beſeech you ſuffer them to be effectually enforced. The point which I will preſſe for uſe and application, is that which is both the ſcope and the thread of this Text, namely, the unitie of God and of the Mediator. The uſe we ſhould make hereof, is for inſtruction, and imitation: and it is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; ſpeciall, for Magiſtrates; generall, for all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>Firſt (I ſay) for Magiſtrates. God is ſaid to be one to all, that is, without all reſpect of perſons: and therefore foraſmuch as Princes, Magiſtrates and Iudges are ſtiled
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2516:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Gods in Scripture,<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> as being the Lievetenants of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, and as it were the finger of that hand that ruleth the whole world: they ſhould imitate him; be one to all, as he is one; be no reſpecters of perſons, as there is no reſpect of perſons with him. as they ſtand in Gods place, ſo ſhould they walke in Gods path,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.1.</note> being followers of him as deare children. To this purpoſe there are manie precepts in the Law: <hi>Deut. 1.17. Yee ſhall heare the ſmall as well as the great. Deut. 16.9. Wrest not the Law, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect anie mans perſon, neyther take reward. Levit. 19.15. Thou ſhalt not favour the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mightie, but thou ſhalt judge thy neighbour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly. For it is not good to have reſpect of anie perſon in judgement, Prov. 24.23.</hi> The Thebanes hereupon portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Iudges blinde, with eates, and without hands: blinde, that he might not diſtinguiſh perſons, friend from foe: with eares, that he might heare both parties indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently: without hands, that he might not receive gifts to corrupt iuſtice; <hi>For the gift blindeth the wiſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteth the words of the righteous, Exod. 23.8.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point; I could wiſh that all who are in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, would alwayes have before their eyes that charge which <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> gave unto his Iudges: <hi>2. Chron. 19.6. And he ſaid to the Iudges, Take heed what yee doe: for yee execute not the judgement of man, but of the Lord—Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now let the feare of the Lord be with you; take heed and doe it: for there is no iniquitie with the Lord our God, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect of perſons, nor receiving of reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſcond uſe is generall for all Chriſtians: If God be one, the mediator one; then ſhould we likewiſe be one. So the Apoſtle reaſoneth, <hi>Eph. 4.4. There is one bodie, one ſpirit, one hope, one Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and father of all.</hi> whereupon followeth the concluſion, ſet downe <hi>verſ. 3.</hi> that we <hi>ſhould endevour to keepe the unitie
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2516:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi> So ſay I: There is one God and one Mediator; and therefore ſhould wee who worſhip this one God, through this one Mediator, be one, as they are one. But how ſhould we be one? One in opinion, one in affection. Firſt (I ſay) one in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; all holding rhe ſame things, beleeving the ſame things, teaching the ſame things, worſhipping God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame maner: for looke how commendable varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is in all other things, it is as much to be abhorred in religion. even thoſe who have held the greateſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, hold that there is but one truth. I never read of more then one hereticke, that held all hereſies true: <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtrius</hi> relateth the opinion of one <hi>Rhetorius,</hi> who ſaid that all religions did well. and which is much like unto this, there was in the ſame age, a fooliſh franticke fellow named <hi>Postellus,</hi> wrote a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wherein hee taketh upon him to reconcile all the religions of all nations, and calleth it <hi>Concordiam Orbis.</hi> Yea and little better are thoſe, who would make a reconciliation betweene the Papiſts &amp; us, being altogether indifferent in things moſt different. They are kind-hearted Philiſtims that would bring the Arke of God and Dagon under one roofe: they are of his mind that <hi>Turonenſis</hi> writeth of, who ſaid, It is beſt of all, <hi>ſi &amp; illa, &amp; illa colantur; neque eſſe noxium ſi inter gentilium aras &amp; Dei eccleſiam quis tranſiens, utra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que veneretur.</hi> They are (as one ſaith) the ghoſts of that heretick <hi>Apelles,</hi> whoſe ſpeech it was, That it is ſufficient to beleeve in Chriſt crucified, and that there ſhould be no diſcuſsing of the particular warrants and reaſons of our faith: Or the brood of <hi>Leonas,</hi> one of the Courtiers of <hi>Constantius,</hi> and his Deputie in the Seleucian Councell, who when the Fathers hotely contended, as there was good cauſe, for the conſubſtantialitie of the Sonne: <hi>Get you home</hi> (ſaid be) <hi>and trouble not the Church with theſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2516:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>trifles.</hi> Theſe things ſeemed but trifles unto carnall men, yet were they matters of great importance: and ſo be the differences betweene us and the Papiſts, of ſuch weight as thereupon dependeth the truth of Gods worſhip, the life of his Church, the ſalvation of our ſoules. And therefore no hope of peace; but though manie meanes of reconciliation have beene uſed, yet never anie could prevaile. The Emperours, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and <hi>Maximilian,</hi> travelled painfully herein, and by their appointment <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander,</hi> a great and learned Papiſt, drew a proiect to ſhew his iudgement; ſo did <hi>Fricius</hi> and the Interimiſts: but all was in vaine; for Babylon could not be cured, her grapes were become as the grapes of Admah, and her vine as the vine of Tſeboim. And as ſhe could not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, ſo we could not admit of anie agreement by mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a middle courſe: <hi>For the truth it is on high</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>) <hi>they may aſcend to us, but for us to goe downe to them, it is neyther ſafe nor honest.</hi> Now it is no more plaine that the Citie of Rome hath deſcended from the ſeven hills, on which it was ſeated in old times, unto the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian plaines that lye below; than it is, that the Church of Rome hath fallen away from that faith which once was commended in her. <hi>Bethel</hi> is become <hi>Bethaven,</hi> the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full citie is become an harlot, her ſilver is turned into droſſe: ſo that unleſſe wee would betray the truth, wee we cannot yeeld to them in anie thing wherein they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if there be anie agreement amongſt us, they muſt come out of Babell, that is, wholly renounce their owne parts, and ioyne hands with us; whereof there is but little hope, when we conſider what ſmall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Reformation hath taken in this kingdome theſe yeares paſt. As king <hi>Ioaſh</hi> asked <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the high Prieſt,<note place="margin">2. King. 12.7.</note> and the other Prieſts, why they did not repayre the ruins of the Temple; ſo may our truly religions King queſtion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2516:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>us that are the Prieſts, why the Temple of the Lord is ſo long in repayring in this land: nay, what is the cauſe that the ruines of the Temple grow greater everie day; more falling away from the truth, than that are reclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from errour? Surely the cauſes hereof are manifeſt: give me leave to obſerve unto you ſuch as I hold to bee the chiefe things that continue this people in their blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hinders reformation.</p>
            <p>The firſt is their cuſtome and long continuance in errour, there being nothing harder than to breake an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant man of his cuſtome.<note place="margin">De doctrinâ Chriſt. l. 4. c. 24.</note> S. <hi>Augustine</hi> comming to Ceſarea, where the people had an ancient cuſtome once a yeare, for certaine dayes together, to divide themſelves into parts, and throw ſtones one at another, whereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie were ſlaine; found it an exceeding hard matter to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from it. This is noted by that Father, to have hindred the reformation of the Donatiſts: <hi>Some were bound not by truth, but by an hard knot of obdurate custome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 48.</note> &amp;c. And ſurely this is a people, of all other moſt zealous of their ancient cuſtomes. Secondly, the ſocietie and alliance, whereby they are linked one to another, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayneth them; being aſhamed and afraid to part with their acquaintance. This is noted by S. <hi>Baſil</hi> to be the thing that hindred the converſion of the Arrians in his time:<note place="margin">Epiſt. 70.</note> 
               <hi>There is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſmall hope of reducing them to the truth, who are linked to hereticks with the band of long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie.</hi> and S. <hi>Austin</hi> yeeldeth the ſame reaſon, why the Donatiſts in his age could not be reclaimed:<note place="margin">Epiſt. 48 ad Vincent.</note> 
               <hi>How many</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>being moved with the truth, would have beene good Catholicks, and yet deferred it, fearing the offence of their friends.</hi> So have I heard manie ſay in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; <hi>If ſuch and ſuch men would goe to Church, I would goe alſo: but if I ſhould begin, I ſhould have the ill will of all the country.</hi> Thirdly, the buſie trafficking of Prieſts and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2516:24"/>Ieſuites for the maintenance of their great goddeſſe <hi>Diana,</hi> by whom they have their living. What skilfull workemen they are, and how cunningly they keep them in blindeneſſe, were long to relate: this, I hope, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently knowne unto our State, that they have beene the chiefe cauſes, not only of the peoples unconformitie in religion; but alſo of all their treaſons &amp; rebellions. The people are like the Sea, and the Prieſts are like the winde: the ſea of it ſelfe would be calme, if the winde did not ſet it in agitation; ſo would the people, but for the Prieſts. The fourth cauſe, is the want of a ſufficient Miniſtry. In manie places there is no Miniſter at all; in manie places a Miniſter as good as none, even a dumb dogge that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not barke, an idoll ſhepheard who is not apt to teach, not able to confute: in other places a lewd and ſcandalous Miniſter, whoſe not Goſpel-like behaviour is a ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling blocke to them that are without. Even as the Prince of Cuba in India, ſaid he would not goe to heaven,<note place="margin">Span. col. p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> if the Spaniards went thither; becauſe he thought that could be no good place, where ſuch cruell tyrants were: ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of this countrey will not be of our religion, becauſe they thinke that can be no true religion, which hath ſo unconſcionable profeſſors and Miniſters. And the chiefe cauſe of this want of a ſufficient miniſtry, is lacke of maintenance: for as there could be no Phyſitian in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemon, becauſe there was no rewards; ſo neyther can there be ſufficient Miniſters here, for want of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. for our great <hi>Nebuchadnezzers</hi> will not allow us ſo much maintenance, as to keep life and ſoule together. We would be content with <hi>Davids</hi> order, albeit a verie unrighteous one; to divide with <hi>Ziba:</hi> but covetous <hi>Ziba</hi> taketh all away, both ſmall and great, both Tythe and offering. He will be both Lord, and Parſon, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car; and it is pittie that he is not brought to be Curate
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2516:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>too. The laſt thing I will obſerve, that hindreth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of this land, is, the miſeducation of our youth; all of them being brought up beyond the Seas, or elſe taught at home by Popiſh Schoolemaſters, who are no more carefull to teach them the Romane tongue, than they are to inſtruct them in the Romiſh faith.</p>
            <p>Thus have I diſcovered the cauſes of our ſickneſſe, hoping that we ſhall receive ſome helpe and comfort by your meanes. For I doubt not (right Honourable) but what was the intent of <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> in ſending his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 17.</note> the ſame was the purpoſe of our gracious Soveraigne, in ſending you; namely, for the repayring of the Temple, and that the people might be taught in the Law of the Lord: for the like choyce of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners hath beene made; ſome nobles, ſome Prieſts and Levites, ſome learned Scribes: and the like charge hath beene given unto you, that ye looke to the good of the Church. And therefore, though I may not ſeeme to preſcribe, yet give me leave to entreat you that yee would take into your chiefeſt care the miſerable eſtate of this Church: and as yee have heard the cauſes of her ruine, ſo ye would labour to remove them, by applying of fit remedies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which in my weake iudgement, are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">Whereas cuſtome and continuance in error, is a maine hinderance unto reformation: the remedie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this is, That ſome compulſion be uſed; for olde ſores are not cured without cutting and lancing: And feare is that which will overcome cuſtome; as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the Antiochians, who though they had a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to waſh themſelves in the Bathes, yet the King forbidding them, they all left for feare of his diſpleaſure. Whereupon S. <hi>Chryſostome</hi> doth conclude after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;<note place="margin">Hom. 14. ad pop. Antioch.</note> 
               <hi>Loe, you may ſee that where feare is, there our wonted custome is left preſently: feare eaſily overmasters custome,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2516:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>though it be never ſo ancient.</hi> The ſame Father in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, maketh mention of one,<note place="margin">Hom 7. ad pop. Ant.</note> who had got an ill-favoured faſhion of moving his right ſhoulder when hee went; which yet he corrected by laying a ſword over it, in ſuch maner, that it ſhould be in danger of cutting, if ſo it moved: and ſo by feare of inciſion, he taught his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der better manners and motions. In like maner ſhould you who have authoritie, deale with thoſe who are blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with long cuſtome in error. For (ſaith S. <hi>Austin</hi>) <hi>ſi doceantur &amp; non terreantur, vetustate conſuetudinis obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati, ad capeſcendam ſalutis viam pigrius ſurgent.</hi> You are the ſecond ſervants of our Lord, ſent forth with this commiſsion, <hi>Compell them to come in, that my houſe may be full.</hi> Yee muſt compell them by lawes and puniſhments, as <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> writeth unto <hi>Eſdras: Whoſoever will not do the law of thy God, and the Kings law, let him have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without delay, whether it be unto death, or to baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to confiſcation of goods, or to impriſonment.</hi> Thus King <hi>Aſa</hi> enacted, that, <hi>If any vvould not ſeeke the Lord God of Iſrael, he ſhould be ſlaine, 2. Chron. 15.13.</hi> So <hi>Ioſiah compelled all that were found in Iſrael, to ſerve the Lord their God, 2. Chron. 34.33.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 48.</note> 
               <hi>Constantine</hi> the great (as S <hi>Augustine</hi> witneſſeth) decreed againſt the Sacrifices of Pagans, upon paine of death: againſt wilful heretickes, upon confiſcation of their goods. The godly Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Decem libris auri mutotare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Aug. ep. 50.</note> being moved therunto by the zealous Biſhop <hi>Amphilochius,</hi> baniſhed all the Arrians out of his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the yonger, ſet a fine of ten pounds of Golde upon the Donatiſts, who were the Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants of that age: which, as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> witneſſeth, had a verie good ſucceſſe; For (ſaith he) <hi>thereby many of them were moved to profeſſe Religion. and though at first they did profeſſe it meerely by compulſion: yet afterwards they profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed onely for devotion.</hi> Theſe were the proceedings of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2516:26"/>godly Kings and Emperours, againſt ſuch as would not conforme themſelves to the true worſhip of God, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the lawes of the land. In alledging whereof, let no man thinke that I would ſeeme to preſcribe rules to Authoritie; farre be that from me: or that I would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſivade extraordinarie ſevere courſes to be taken with a blinde and miſled people. God is my witneſſe, I ſeeke not theirs, but them: my only purpoſe is to iuſtifie the law of this land, and practiſe of our Church, and that our people may ſee what a milde government they live under, if they will but conſider, how their Fines, beſides that they are ſo neglected in the execution, that the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth man is not charged with them; are even in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a great deale lighter, than thoſe puniſhments which formerly have beene inflicted by godly Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, upon offendors of the like nature. But eſpecially they muſt confeſſe, that they are gently entreated, if they will remember what was the proceedings of their Church againſt us: for in former ages they proceeded againſt the Waldenſes, and the firſt reformers of our Church and even at this time they doe proceed againſt Proteſtants in other countries, not with mulcts and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment; but with ſword, fire, and fagot. They fyne them indeed, but it is with fire; as witneſſe their houſes of Inquiſition in Spaine and Italy, and their bloody wars in France and Germanie, for the cauſe of religion. But the time of retribution will come, and God will move Kings and Magiſtrates, to harken to that exhortation, <hi>Rev. 18.6.</hi> which is directed unto them, and directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth theſe times of ours: <hi>Reward her even as ſhe hath rewarded you: give her double according to her workes, and in the cup that ſhe hath filled to you, fill her the double. Pſal. 137.8. O daughter of Babel worthy to be destroyed, bleſſed ſhall he be that rewardeth thee, as thou hast ſerved us. Bleſſed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2516:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall he be that taketh and daſheth thy children against the ſtones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas feare of men reſtrayneth manie from ioyning with us: The remedie to be uſed againſt this, is, to preſſe and urge firſt and chiefly the great ones; for they cannot pleade this, That they dare not for their friends. for the eyes of the people are upon them, and all are readie to follow them, not to leade them. 3 Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Prieſts and Ieſuites are a great let unto reformation; for remedie againſt this, let a ſevere courſe be taken with them for they are the ſeducers of the people, inſtruments of Idolatry, authors of rebellion, bellowes and brands of ſedition. Ye ſhall ſcarce ever reade in the old Teſtament of anie reformation of religion, and aboliſhing of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but the Prieſts were cut off: <hi>Elijah</hi> ſlew all the Prieſts of Baal, <hi>1. King. 18.40.</hi> ſo did <hi>Iehu, 2. King. 10.25. Ioaſh</hi> the King, and <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the Prieſt, with all the people, ſlew <hi>Mattan</hi> the Prieſt of Baall before the Altars, <hi>2. Chron. 23.17.</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah</hi> burnt the bones of the Prieſts upon their Altars, <hi>2. Chron. 34.5.</hi> And though our Prieſts deſerve no leſſe, yet I deſire not their blood, but onely that they might be removed, and reſtrained from ſeducing of the people: for in this queſtion of putting hereticks to death, as in all other, I ſubmit my ſelfe to the iudgement of our Church, and practiſe of our countrey; which never put anie to death, <hi>religionis cauſa merae, ſed mixtae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tortur. tor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p 133.</note> 
               <hi>mixtae cum mala mente &amp; ſide in principem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth cauſe of their blindneſs and errour, is want of a ſufficient Miniſtrie, cauſed through the want of maintenance: for remedie againſt this, great care would be taken for to plant able and painefull Miniſters, and to provide a ſufficient maintenance for them. Thus <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> appointed Prieſts and Levites, and provided for their living: For <hi>he commanded the people to give the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2516:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Priests and Levites, that they might be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Law of the Lord, 2. Chron. 31.4.</hi> there is a good precedent for you. We have ſuch an <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but we lack ſuch ſubiects to obey: for our Church-robbers, albeit commanded by the King, yet will not give the Prieſts their owne portion, nor anie part of their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not the meaneſt offering; all is too little to buy and maintaine their ſacrilegious honour. But ſurely if they be not compelled to allow ſome competent mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for a Miniſter, but their impropriations be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; it is but in vaine to looke for anie reformation. I will ſay that the old ſaying is like to prove a true propheſie; <hi>Hibernia ante diem judicij non reformabitur.</hi> The laſt thing I named that hindreth a reformation, is the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of their youth: for remedie againſt this, a courſe would be taken, that none be ſuffered to go beyond Seas for to ſtudie; that no Popiſh Schoole-maſters be permitted at home, and that all, who are of abilitie, bee compelled to ſend their children to be brought up in our Schooles. There hath beene directions given to this purpoſe, but there is no ſuch thing performed: that evill is not cured but increaſed.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe things were done; Severe puniſhments inflicted, The great ones chiefely urged, The Prieſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, Able Miniſters planted, Popiſh Schooles and Schoole maſters reſtrained: there were ſome hope that they would ioyne with us, and all of us become one Church and one ſheepefold, as there is one God and one Mediator.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould I ſpeake of an unitie with Papiſts, while we are not all one amongſt our ſelves; but ſtill conteſting about trifles,<note place="margin">5 King. 2.5.</note> and (as it is ſaid of <hi>Ioah</hi>) <hi>ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the blood of warre in peace?</hi> which gives occaſion to the Papiſts to inſult over us, crying out, That we are not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2516:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>the true Church, becauſe divided in ſundry ſects and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions. which was the rotten argument of prophane <hi>Celſus; Christianos non habere veram religionem, quod in varias ſectas diviſi eſſent.</hi> Here I could anſwer;
<list>
                  <item>firſt; That unitie is no propertie of the Church, being not alwayes inſeparably and incommunicably found therein.</item>
                  <item>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that manie falſe Churches have an agreement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, that the true Church was never without diviſions.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, that our differences are not ſo great nor ſo manie, as our adverſaries would make men beleeve;</item>
               </list>
but a great part of them, are inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our adverſaries: another part concerne not us, nor any of our Church, but are the doctrines of certaine ſects and hereticks which have ſprung up with the revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved light of the Goſpell, and are gone out of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches: ſome of them are onely quatrels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſome particular men, not anie differences between Churches; and the greateſt part of them all, are not reall but verbal, not in matters of faith, but about ceremonies and matters of no importance: finally, that there is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcord in the Church of Rome; for there is not one point in all divinitie (except thoſe wherein wee accord with them) wherein they all ſpeake the ſame. But albert theſe things being all true (as were eaſie to prove) be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſtop the mouthes of the adverſaries; yet I could rather wiſh, that we did not need to uſe this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie: for certainly this earth hath nothing more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, than the civill iarres of one faith. <hi>Constantine</hi> the Emperour ſaid unto the Biſhops of the Councell of Nice,<note place="margin">Zozom. l. 1. c. 17.</note> That he thought this worſe than all the evils to be utrered, that he ſaw the Church of God diſſenting by contentions, and contrarie opinions. For firſt, diviſion in faith, hath ever beene a mother of Atheiſme. <hi>Sozomen</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2516:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. cap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>The contrarieties of opinions among the learned at that time, was ſo ſcandalous, that it turned manie away from embracing the Christian Religion.</hi> and ſo at this time there be manie who will be of no religion, till they ſee the differences amongſt the learned reconciled. Yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention doth extinguiſh the verie life of Religion, which is brotherly love: and therefore they who make ſo much adoe about ceremonies, had need to take heed, that in the meane time they loſe not that which is more pretious, even Chriſtian charitie it ſelfe. They are like unto a man who came to a Phyſitian, to deſire a cure for the Whitlay in his finger; and while the Phyſitian looketh upon him, he perceiveth death in his face. Secondly, by our contentions our adverſaries get advantage. It was a true ſpeech, cyted from that Father S <hi>Hilary,</hi> by <hi>Bellarm. Bellum haereticorum, pax eſt eccleſiae:</hi> but our experience doth invert it upon us; <hi>Bellum eccleſiae pax haereticorum.</hi> Our diſcord is their muſicke, our ruine their glory: they laugh, and ſcorne, and clap their hands at our bickerings. Thirdly, it is a moſt grievous oftence againſt God to rent the Church, which is his bodie, with ſchiſmes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions: it is no leſſe than ſacriledge, no better than Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; For (as an ancient Father ſaith) <hi>Non minor is est laudis non ſcindere eccleſiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyoniſ. apud Niceph.</note> 
               <hi>quam idolo non ſacrificare.</hi> S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> thought that God ſent the perſecutions of his time,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. epiſt. 4.</note> for no other cauſe than their contentions. and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> beginning to entreat of the bloodie perſecution which the Church ſuffered under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 1. hift. c. 2.</note> ſaith, <hi>The contentions of the learned therein, was the cauſe.</hi> And why may not I ſay, That it was for this ſame cauſe, that God at this time ſuffereth our neighbour Churches to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo cruell perſecution, and threatneth the like iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt us? he will try if affliction can humble us,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2516:28"/>and the rage of the common enemie make us friends. <hi>For ſo doe men uſe</hi> (ſaith an old Hiſtory, ſpeaking of this matter) <hi>as long as ſtrangers wrong them, to hold together;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zozom. l. 6. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>but vvhen they are delivered from outward troubles, then they fall out among themſelves.</hi> Theſe be the hurts we ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain by our diſſentions: And therfore if ever we would ſee the good dayes of the Goſpell, the flouriſhing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the unhorſing and confuſion of the ſtrumpet Rome, if wee deſire to eſcape the iudgements of God, which did fall upon the primitive Church for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions: let us labour to reconcile our ſelves, and at length to embrace unitie; let us all compoſe our ſelves to peace and love. <hi>Oh pray for the peace of Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, thankes be to God, the Church of this land, is not much troubled with ſuch iarres; and therefore I come to the other ſort of unitie: As wee are one in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſo muſt we be one in affection. Ye that are of one Church, and profeſſe one faith, <hi>be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord and of one judgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>that nothing be done through contention and vaine-glory, &amp;c.</hi> Let us dwell together as brethren,<note place="margin">Pſal 13 3.1.</note> which is a good and comely thing: let us love one another, as God hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us;<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.35.</note> for hereby ſhall it be knowne that we are Chriſts diſciples, if we love one another. This is indeed the mark of a Chriſtian, the commandement of God, the fulfilling of the law: and eſpecially at this time, when we celebrate this Feaſt of <hi>Pentecost,</hi> ſhould our hearts be united toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, through love. For it is ſaid when the Apoſtles were wayting for the comming of the holy Ghoſt on the day of Pentecoſt, that <hi>they were all</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Act. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>with one accord in one place.</hi> and then did the Spirit come downe upon them in a viſible ſhape. So if wee would have the holy Ghoſt to deſcend on us this day, and every day, though not in a viſible ſhape, yet in inviſible favours, leading us
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2516:29"/>into all truth, and making our whole life a merry Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontide: we muſt be, as the Apoſtles were, <hi>unanimes,</hi> with one accord in one place. For he is the ſpirit of love, and will not reſt in a contentious heart: but where there is unitie of ſpirit, there doth reſt this ſpirit of unitie; and the fruit of this ſpirit is <hi>Love, joy, peace, long ſuffering, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but on the other part, <hi>Hatred, variance, emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions,</hi> are not the fruits of the ſpirit, but the workes of the fleſh. Wherefore ſince it is ſo, I beſeech you, Men, Brethren, and Fathers, let mee ſpeake to you in the words of the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul: Put on (as the elect of God holy and beloved) bowels of mercie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekeneſſe, long ſuffering: forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrell against any: even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo doe yee. And above all theſe things, put on Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, which is the bond of perfectneſſe. And let the peace of God rule in your hearts.</hi> So ſhall we be one, as God is one and the Mediator one:<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in this life, one amongſt our ſelves; and the life to come, one with God in glory. <hi>To this one</hi> God, <hi>&amp;c. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2516:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
